[Music]
everybody you are back it is Jeff Murphy
this is the Jack McGee life podcast you
can find me Jack Murphy at Jack Murphy
live on Twitter Jack Murphy live.com
Jack Murray live all over the internet
actually I planned it exactly that way
you can also come check me out as a
liminal order that's liminal - order
calm that is our international almonds
mail fraternity where we work hard to
improve ourselves that we can be a
better service to our families our
community and our nation and today I
have a fantastic guest somebody I have
been really looking forward to talk to
his name is Michael Miller man he has a
PhD in political science he has studied
philosophy he has his own similar story
as I do of finding challenges in this
world of studying things and exploring
ideas and just taking a look at what's
around us in this world and finding
resistance and especially in academia so
today we're going to do a special
podcast I'm calling it Dugan for dummies
and that's Alexander Dugan the Russian
philosopher to be honest I don't really
know too terribly much about Alexander
Dugan or his relationship with Heidegger
and so I am interested to learn a lot
more about that and I'm so excited to
have you here Michael how are you doing
today welcome to the show thanks very
much for having me
going well pretty excited great good
good I want to set the table a little
bit with a little bit of your background
story you have an experience that is
similar to a lot of other folks these
days people to folks who are people who
are out sort of on the edge willing to
engage with ideas that they may not
agree with willing to engage with ideas
that people may find radical or
off-the-wall and so you've experienced a
little bit of canceled culture yourself
why don't you tell us a little bit about
that I think the story starts about
while you're trying to get your PhD is
that right yeah it goes back a little
bit earlier so let me just set it up I
was an undergraduate in philosophy at
the University of British Columbia and I
was studying basically Plato Aristotle
some of the main texts you study when
you do a program in philosophy and at
some point I got the interest in
learning technical philosophical
vocabulary in Russian
and the reason I got that interest is
that my family's from the former Soviet
Union
we spoke some Russian in the household
growing up and I had been even vaguely
aware of some tradition of Russian
mysticism and sort of these Russian
religious thinkers in the 19th century
like Vladimir Solovyov for example is
one of them and I developed this
interest in knowing for example how to
say the key terms of a philosophical
lexicon in Russian so in English you
know there's like I mean you may or may
not know there's a substance accident
essence existence all that - all the
terms that have been passed down from
Greek to Latin and eventually to English
I wanted to know them in Russian so I
proposed to do a translation of some
Russian philosopher in my department and
I got the green light to do that they
said just find a contemporary russian
philosopher and an older russian
philosopher and you can do that we'll
work with you to translate them and see
what comes out of it so at this time I
did not know who Alexander Dugan was
yeah it was my task to go try to find a
contemporary philosopher because this
guy had an interest in didn't really
count you know 1900 is a little bit
before our time that's when some of you
have died so at the same time I was
reading a journal called Azur a zu re
okay and I encountered an article there
called Alexander do get Dugan profit of
a new Russian Empire something like that
okay and this article was just gripping
really gripping because it said that
Dugan was this sort of mystical
philosopher king who you couldn't
understand Russia if you didn't
understand its deepest identity its
spiritual soul and that Dugan was really
your window into that deep understanding
of Russia so the article had touched a
few things that are just personally
deeply very interesting to me but again
the figure of the philosopher King which
comes from Plato's Republic and is just
you know as I was studying in the
department that was one of the things
that stood out for me the idea that you
have the wise should be the
legislators you know or the wise should
be the ones who configure political life
so all of that came out in this article
another thing that was really as I say
gripping was there was a story that he
had been kicked out of Ukraine I mean
because he has some thoughts about
Ukrainian geopolitics that don't
necessarily square with their own self
understanding and that the same day that
he was kicked out of Ukraine the Russian
government expelled Ukrainian ambassador
and his family from Russia so there was
to see like that a state has the back of
this weird mystical philosopher who
somehow has penetrated the depths of the
Russian soil all of that was just that
was just interesting okay yeah definite
them up and I found a speech of his this
must have been 2010 or 11 I couldn't say
exactly something around that time I
looked them up and I found a speech
there's a five-minute talk on YouTube
about something he called the fourth
political theory right something he's
known for now because a book called the
fourth political theory was published in
2012 and I helped to translate it which
got the ball rolling for all of these
all of the canceled culture blow back
but at the time it was just an
interesting lecture I heard you know so
that I basically went on his Russian
Wikipedia saw he had a book called the
fourth political theory ran it by my
supervisor and said why don't we start
here you know this scene this is all I
know about the guy it's really
fascinating that five minute lecture
also pulled me in for reasons I can
explain and he said sure let's do it I
started translating the book
eventually he my supervisor encouraged
me to get in touch with Dugan about
having the translation published because
this supervisor again at the
undergraduate level he was amazed
this was rate at the time that Vladimir
Putin was basically announcing that
Russia was going to adopt Duggan's
ideology as its official worldview right
so he's reading this and he's saying oh
my god this is amazing
you have to get this published right so
he said email email Dugan reach out to
him and see what's going on so I did I
shot him I sent him an email
absolutely I think I first tried finding
like his phone number at the time he was
at Moscow State University was very hard
to try to track him down somehow I can't
remember I found his email address shot
him an email and he said there's already
a translation underway that was under
caught under contract with the
publishing house called arctos so I got
in touch with them and they said hey
let's take what you've done of the
translation with what we've done of the
translation we have a conference coming
up shortly we'd love to have the book
ready by then let's combine what we have
and what you have and we'll put this out
this was in July 2012 so they did I was
thrilled undergraduate okay first
official book translation of Alexander
Dugan in English I'd made my
contribution I thought it was very
interesting sort of my supervisor got it
published you know I was so glad to see
on the inside cover my name I felt like
I was making a contribution to political
theory and I took that going into my
masters in PhD program saying hey look
I'm translating Russian political
philosophy I'm putting this guy on the
table I'm helping you understand
something that is crucial geopolitically
politically and philosophically like
what more cuz you basically want I
thought they were going to eat this up
because my understanding is basically it
sounds perfect right so I word on my
sleeve I told the people at the
University of Toronto where I did my
masters in PhD that thought I'm doing
this dougen wrote me a letter of
reference to get into the program as I
say he was an academic at the time among
other things and I continued to
translate but by the time word got out
that Toronto has this expert on Duggan's
thought I was invited onto a Canadian
television program for an interview
about him an article had just come out
called Putin's brain positioning do
as the mastermind of not wrongly really
as the mastermind of Putin's
geopolitical vision in Ukraine and our
end around the world and so this TV
program invited me on for an interview I
did it I thought it went well they
thought it went well and suddenly it
started to circulate you know how these
things work people were amazed I still
get letters this was 2 December 2014 I
still get emails I still get letters for
people saying that was like eye opening
for them they had never heard a Russian
perspective or a critical perspective or
a thinker on the right a conservative a
traditionalist they had never heard any
of that presented just on like for what
it is like to try to understand it to
try to articulate it and to try to
present it all they either thought you
know you look at whether it's you know
you look at Russia or you look at
conservatives you look at
traditionalists and all you do is say
we're fascists neo-fascist Nazis
you know this logic right anything that
doesn't fall into the status quo is
somehow outside of it is automatically
branded and that's funnily enough what
happened when I came back to the
University after the TV interview so I
gave the interview people around the
world are writing to me it's blowing up
it was one of their big fit while
blowing up it's almost at a hundred
thousand views which for that particular
station it's not so bad and then before
too long I got hauled into the offices
of my dissertation supervisor at the
University of Toronto and the
railroading began all right before we
before we get too much further with that
can turn the gain down on your vault on
your microphone just a smidge and can
you explain why it is that it's
important that you have like a committee
like your PhD committee I'm not sure
everybody understands yeah is that
better yeah it's better okay sorry
no problem past so in a in a graduate
program what you do is you spend three
or four some people spend more but let's
say three to four years on a major
research project and usually the way it
works is you have one supervisor who
works with you on that project they
basically take you under their wing you
share your your chapters with them and
they give you critical feedback
your closest point of contact but in
order down the road to defend that
dissertation which you have to do to
graduate from the program you have to do
it before a committee of members and
those members sign an agreement with you
at the proposal stage so first you
propose the project you want to do it's
like a 20 page proposal for example they
say I'll sign off they say this is going
to be a contribution to the literature
this is methodologically sound it's
interesting and yeah you know we're
we're here to have you defend this and
then off you go you do the research and
hopefully at the end of three years you
have something that you can defend in
order to graduate so I was in that
process but I was very early in it I
just had the proposal accepted so I had
the committee people who had agreed to
work with me they knew I was into Dugan
I've been talking about it
well I hadn't been talking about it
since I got there but you know I
mentioned it because I was proud of it
mm-hmm I was getting good grades so
there's no issue there about all of the
technicalities were in order right my
teaching reviews were good as a TA so
everything's University of Toronto right
yeah so for those of you who don't know
and it's fine if you don't the
University of Toronto is it's important
and for a few reasons actually because
number one it's considered the best
school in Canada so you would expect
this to be the place where you have the
most serious examination especially in a
department of okay I was in a department
of political science by now and the way
political science works is there are
subfields so somebody works on
International Relations somebody can
work on development studies American
politics my subfield of political
science is called political theory
that's where the philosophy happens
that's where you do the careful readings
of theoretical texts of classics and all
of that and so the fact that my work was
so badly received not because of its
quality but but because of the logic of
cancel' culture here in a way right
somehow I touched a nerve and it wasn't
supposed to happen because the
Department of Political Science at the
best university in Canada in that
subfield where you're supposed to think
is the last place in principle you would
expect or where I expected
to have the kind of reaction that that
that TV interview eventually got right
so what year was this that you were
putting your committee together so they
had signed off it was either late 2014
or early 2015
so pretty much rate at the time that I
gave the interview I had already had the
project accepted I already had a chapter
that got a pretty good review from my
supervisor in fact that said it was
quite good really good and I had a whole
committee so I was sailing actually I
felt when I thought that I was sailing
and for context isn't University of
Toronto where Jordan Peterson was yes it
is
yes it is but that his his sort of
Fiasco came a little bit later a couple
years later now yeah it's funny because
some online conspiracy theorists who
later learned that I was there and he
was there we both work on Heidegger you
know they started to draw connection
that he's secretly a du Guinness and
things like that but you know you can
count on the conspiracy theorist to draw
connections at will right right okay so
they everybody starts to find out what
you're doing everything seems like it's
gonna be moving ahead full steam and
then what happens yeah so I got an email
that said from my supervisors I said hey
I'd like to have a meeting with you in
the office and do you mind if this other
professor who's not on my committee
joins I said no no problem at all you
know let's have the meeting and I got to
tell you in retrospect it is what it is
but at the time I thought this is great
these guys are calling me in because I
just sent them my chapter which they you
know my supervisor said the chapter was
great so I said look I'm ahead of the
curve things are going well for sure
we're gonna be planning out like my next
steps this is all about you know me
finishing in four years instead of five
and about planning out my next
professional steps like I was sure that
this was all gravy
you know I did not see the bus coming
okay so I went into his office and very
somber Lou you know closes the door sits
down Michael
I saw your video on that TV program and
I have something I'd like to say to you
it takes out a piece of paper says I'm
too emotional I can't even say this too
I had to write it out as a letter and
I'm now I'm going to read it to you boy
and he starts reading me this letter
that he wrote to me
with his witness that he now I
understand you know he called a witness
or his ass is protected whereas I wasn't
given the chance to have anything like
that for my own protection so to speak
so he starts reading me this letter and
you know it's when I first heard about
Dugan I just thought it was this
harmless thing but then I looked them up
and I see he's he and then it started
are you a anti-semite you support this
or you extermination astana know that he
would want to do this to me and how can
you do that and it's just every
accusation Under the Sun up to and
including that I'm being used by the
Russians so this was a total total
blindside and I the only thing I regret
is I wish I had said you know you've hit
so many so many points that are just
gonna give me cause to reflect here can
I just just have a copy of the letter so
I can take it home and you know go over
it and do some soul-searching because
that letter was a real work of art but I
didn't I didn't get a copy of the letter
but he he poured out his soul to me out
of concern and it was pretty shocking
actually
so the next day I think like he emailed
me and he said again how can you be
involved with this guy in any way and I
responded that look here's the jeers my
philosophical interest in the guy here's
the truth of the justification like it's
pretty it's pretty straightforward from
my perspective and and really quickly he
he resigned from the committee and then
another member resigned from the
committee and I had the beginning of
what was going to be like a minimum a
six months to a year of like deep hell
at the campus where I didn't have any
supporters except for one this one
committee member who later became my
supervisor she was like the bright light
she's stood by my side she was appalled
that these guys would resign she thought
there was no justification no ground for
it that they were betraying all of their
principles and you got to understand
there are a million nuances here like
one of the members who resigned was the
Strauss Ian who in principle is open to
the study of serious political
philosophy another one of them about a
week before he quit the committee he had
given a public speech in which he said
that in a liberal democracy like ours
there's no need for any
to censor themselves because there's no
persecution for heterodox thought in a
liberal democracy the same person who
said that
one week later resigned from the
committee and they effectively
blacklisted me from academia now at
University of Toronto do they bat an eye
when somebody wants to study I don't
know another lay of Marx for example not
only do they not bat an eye you know
they welcomed with open arms to a
certain extent projects like that and
I'll say in addition you know if you
want to study Islamic fundamentalist
political theory which exists okay you
could do that if you want to study
pretty much any radical political theory
especially on the left or multicultural
radicalism okay if it's Aboriginal
radicalism or something like that that's
fine if it is uh you see what I'm saying
all of that is fine but somehow a
Russian Orthodox conservative whiteness
who's not a liberal and doesn't fit into
you know what I mean
somehow that just there was no way of
making sense of it and they all lost
they all lost their minds and it was it
was a pretty wild ride so I we're
obviously gonna get into the the meat of
it all but I want to just tie this into
a conversation I just had with James
Lindsay the other day who has been
writing a lot about his new book is
called cynical theories and it's all
about how post-modernism went from an
artist etic all the way into applied
postmodern theory and then into sort of
a reified god-like religious
circumstance of philosophy and in there
you know they basically they're arguing
against the liberal liberal political
economy liberal thinking liberal
societies through these philosophies to
what extent do you think that there is
an anti liberalism force train running
through the University of Toronto even
if it's hidden or obscured to what
extent is actually anti-liberal well
look here here's the here's the thing so
if the postmodern left has an anti
liberal animus and it has infiltrated
certain departments or just established
certain departments and it's sometimes
taken over whole you know faculties or
even whole institutions
let's say all of that is accurate okay
but here's the thing usually you have it
set up like you have the post-modern
left attack on liberalism science
rationality freedom rights in that
tradition but what happened at the
University of Toronto did not fall into
that because the people who kicked me
off the committee I mean you know who
resigned the committee and basically as
I say effective lack lists from academia
they were not on the postmodern left and
neither am i so this takes the whole
logic of a campus culture war and
expands it to something that's less
familiar which is that you had basically
it's like center-left Liberals okay and
Center liberals these some of the people
who are on the committee and me doing
research on somebody who criticizes
liberalism but not not from the left
okay so it'll be important to understand
something about where Dugan falls on the
spectrum of political theories to see
this more clearly but basically you
could say this is a bit of a distortion
but still helpful that this was liberals
and on campus blacklisting the study of
right-wing anti liberalism so again
usually the tension is between the left
the post modernists and the scientists
but here is between the Liberals and the
right of liberal critics now you don't
get a lot of right of liberal critics
seriously studied in academia and even
though it's much easier for a student
let's say to name like GJ Berra de Fuko
Marx and many other thinkers if you said
to them okay that's the sort of
tradition of the postmodern left now can
you name to me some serious thinkers who
represent the right right wing
alternative to liberalism they probably
will not be able to do that okay but at
least we would have to say Misha
Heidegger Carl Schmitt Alexander Dugan
and to a certain extent Leo Strauss so
it's a smaller universe but it always
seems to me how are we going to
understand what liberalism is and what
the threats to liberalism are if we're
only always looking to the left and when
we look to the right all we see is
fascism or Nazism well it's more nuanced
than that because these figures on the
right are not identical to one another
and they often disagree with one another
Strauss was very critical of Schmidt
Schmidt and Heidegger are not the same
thing
is his own story so there was this
undiscovered territory on the right and
I said I thought basically like Socrates
when he had to propose his punishment he
said you guys should all give me like a
penthouse suite and you know five
thousand dollars a month reward for what
I've shown you obviously they chose a
different way so I thought similarly you
know I said look you guys have been
completely missing the picture on
right-wing anti liberalism and I'm
giving you not just access to the
figures who belong to that tradition
inherently like Nietzsche let's say but
Alexander Dugan a completely unique
phenomenon that will help you to
understand the possible spectrum of
political theory right and they didn't
see it that way you know it's funny I've
the circles I run into people I talk to
I hear Heidegger in each a a Strauss I
hear these names and the ideas thrown
around all so much that it doesn't even
I don't even stop for a second to think
that it's like a radical thing to think
about or out of the box or something
wild well let me just say on that point
I mean it's one of the reasons I feel
more at home outside of academia now
because I spent so many years there okay
well through my undergraduate the
masters the PhD that the the environment
on one hand there's the serious study of
old texts and there is to some extent
you know high standards of scholarship
but there's a much fresher and freer air
outside of academia I have met people
and I've spoken to people this
conversation that we're having now where
it's not only more respectful it is
truer to the thought it's true it to the
text it it's not so dogmatically closed
at the outset that it can't possibly
learn anything and and I wasn't
expecting that at the University but
unfortunately I found that other people
find it in different ways for different
reasons and I think this space that you
were helping to create and that other
people are involved in outside of
academia where ideas they don't have to
be on the right but they but if you're
thinking some of them will be on the
right some of them will be on the left
some of them will be elsewhere maybe a
completely different topography
altogether I think outside of the
university is where that is happening
where it's going to continue to happen
and I can tell you that there were
students who came to me after class when
I was a TA and who just still email me
now all the time
and they know that the university is not
the place where they can genuinely think
that's a damn shame but it's also a fact
and it's an opportunity for the people
like yourself and and others as I say
who are keeping the conversation alive
in in print and through podcasts and by
video and it's quite exciting and as I
say a big relief for me in a way finally
to have left
I haven't burned my bridges with
academia I still respect as I say some
components of it but the purest thought
is not happening there yeah it is
unfortunate but it is yet another
example of how there's emerging networks
of people and expertise and
understanding and action in in almost
every realm that is superseding the
established institutions so whether it's
dealing with Corona kovat trying to
understand what's going on there or
dealing with political issues or
economic issues or philosophical issues
or or just the study of knowledge or
whatever it is the the networks that are
forming outside of the institutions are
weird that where the real evolution is
where the action is where the answers
are where the solutions are going to be
found and it's an exciting place to be I
couldn't imagine being on campus right
now they're not not in the least I'm
actually doing my own version of
backfilling my gaps in my education this
conversation is one of them on to be
honest I'm trying to sort of learn the
things that I didn't learn along the way
in school both my masters and bachelor's
um but I wanted to ask a question about
the context what why do you think that
there was such push back to studying
dougen do you was it related do you
think to Trump and Trump's alleged you
know collusion with with Putin and
Russia and like some great fear that
there was going to be like a Russian
takeover of Western Mach I mean it's so
dumb to say but it's a takeover of
Western democracy or some sort of new
dirty alliance between the United States
and Russia or something that Dugan had
something to do with do you think it was
related to Trump at all or did a precede
Trump by just a smidge or is it related
it is related it's related
it's not the only factor but it's
definitely one of the factors so the the
supervisor who will resign first the
next book that he wrote was called
Dangerous Minds
Nietzsche Heidegger and the return of
the far right so smack on the concern
and it's the cover of the book is the
Charlottesville okay so for him it's
like immediately related Heidegger Dugan
Nazis tiki torches it's all the same
soup you know and so that was one part
of it another person who resigned from
the committee he told me at one point
look he told me this in a private in the
coffee shop resignation meeting he said
my son is fighting Islamic terrorists in
the Middle East and you're working on
Dugan who supports Islamic terrorists in
the Middle East and therefore there's
this unbridgeable gap between us you
would just we can't work together
because you're on the side of the enemy
effectively which was well I mean I'll
let people make their own judgment about
whether yeah whether that's real I mean
I'm over here shaking shaking my head
and disgust there's no there was no no
space given to just understanding that
you have to hold even if you don't agree
if even if you think that they're your
enemy it behooves you to study them
in-depth Lee there was no no credence
given to that very little to put it
kindly
but once so one other thing is that
Dugan himself is a multi-faceted
character so if somebody were I mean now
maybe it's different I don't know but at
that time if you were just to google
Alexandre Dugan
pull him up on Wikipedia you might get
the impression you know from whatever
comes up first that he is a to quote you
know somebody's characterization of him
and Applebaum a crackpot you know or
some you could get a bad first
impression of him if you just pull him
up on Wikipedia and they may have
thought that my interest in him was that
I googled something you know what I mean
and he came up and that I'm attracted to
him because he once did an interview
with Ahmadinejad or something like that
but the thing is that he is as I say
multifaceted and I came to his works
from the
walk down you know from the theoretical
the philosophical and I have to tell you
this interesting story so his he has
written about Heidegger he has a few
books on Heidegger but one of them was
published in English that's not one that
I translated although I translated many
others and when again at the University
somebody found out that this person had
a book on Heidegger the rumors
circulated and got back to me he said
that he had said it's not possible that
Dugan wrote that hide of your book
because you can't have a person who at
the same time write serious works of
political philosophy and does like what
we can just call here like shitposting
or you know something like something
like that in brief right that can't be
the same person therefore someone else
might must have written inside of a book
and he thought it had been me so I was
supposedly the ghostwriter of Dugan's
first Heidegger book but in fact it's
just that Dugan is a complicated
multifaceted figure he's as comfortable
lecturing about phenomenology Aristotle
Plato and Heidegger on one hand in ways
that are very good so he's a great I
think lecturer and he knows his material
very well and at the same time you know
he can turn off his interview and go on
the Alex Jones Show and be talking some
something that is uh less familiar to an
academic audience let's say you know and
they weren't able to put those two
things together so the Trump thing yes
the Russia thing yes the fact that they
were faced with someone who doesn't fit
the model of an academic political
philosopher all of that was a part of it
and I got to tell you as much as I
learned writing the dissertation which
was a lot and as much as I learned
reading all of these people and
translating Dugan which I did and
enjoyed and continue to do seeing how
these professors reacted to the whole
thing was probably the most instructive
experience that I had on campus because
it just was every hypocrisy and I held I
held Strauss Ian's
I mean I still hold Strauss in this
regard but I held Strauss ian's in like
the highest regard so I thought that
they were the most willing to look into
philosophical questions without turning
their backs on them and running away
from them and here I definitely had a
mugged by reality type moment but not in
the usual way right well you know
anybody who's interesting and worth
talking to
these days seems to have a similar storm
a similar story like this you know they
say if if you're not getting heat you're
not in the right place you're not on the
right track so clearly you should take
it as a sign that you're doing something
interesting it's something worthwhile
because oh the guys people if you don't
get any heat if you don't get any
pushback what are you doing boring
nobody cares nobody cares and that's it
you know it's a terrible way to live
your life like using that as a metric I
hate like but you know once they hate
does start coming you have to actually
think of it as a pot it's a positive
sign and for me I mean I had an Tifa
come after me I got Docs I got fired I
got called a Nazi and racist and all
this stuff
and that wasn't for studying Dugan or
Heidegger an actual Nazi it was for just
talking about whether or not we should
have sanctuary cities like you know
should our local jurisdictions disregard
federal law like that seems like a
pretty reasonable question to me but I
got fired for it anyway but it was a
blessing in disguise it's almost two
years ago and you know now I get to do
this everyday for my living so it's been
been able to turn it around
and I'm hoping that you will be able to
turn that experience around and I guess
we didn't finish the story but you know
I guess you found some people who were
gonna ended up coming onto the committee
and and and standing up standing by your
side to get this work done that's right
it divided the department divided the
faculty there were realignment of
friendships and of everything like that
but eventually I had I had a very
supportive committee and you know I'd
originally planned it that I would have
like roughly a leftist the liberal and a
conservative so that I was speaking to a
whole spectrum I ended up having like
yeah a postmodern Africanist the rabbi
and you know so a very interesting group
of people but but the dividing line was
those who think students must be subject
to an ideological test and those who
support the philosophical merit of
genuine inquiry so I ended up it was a
blessing in disguise it's continued to
be like I said I've met so many good
people yourself included this is great
and I met so many good people as a
result of what happened I continued to
get letters and emails it's fantastic I
have I shudder when I think about what
my life would have been like if I had
remained on the academic trajectory
where I had to watch my step where I had
to watch my mouth I mean I still do
obviously to a certain extent but not
like it
there there there was basically just a
gag order right
you know I'm thinking back one of my
early philosophy classes was all about
Marx and I know we actually studied on
the Jewish Question and I can't even
remember what my professor said about it
but it was a generally positive Marx
class so I wonder I got to go back and
check my notes it's just crazy to think
that I remember now looking back I
remember reading mark Kusa and like
reading clear clear critical theory and
all kinds of stuff and it was all
presented to me totally as just this is
the way the world is this is the you
know don't even question it there was it
was just all given as a given and I'm
having to go back and and rejigger my
mind so let's let's get started actually
with the material about Dugan and
Heidegger and Strauss a one thing I
wanted to ask you quick I didn't ask
this of Ryan Williams president of the
Claremont Institute as well who's the
Strauss CM guys what what do you mean
when you say Strauss Ian because I hear
that term thrown around and I know my
audience hears it thrown around too what
what does that mean what does that
general outlook or what does that say
about somebody if you call them as
Strauss Ian okay here's how it put it so
first of all joseon's are those people
who share a view that Leo Strauss was a
masterful interpreter of the texts of
political philosophy from Plato to
Nietzsche so not everybody shares that
view there are people who think that
Strauss is way of reading texts is
illegitimate or misleading but for the
most part people who call themselves
joseon's share Roces view of how to read
these texts and what that means is that
you read them with the utmost respect
you don't assume just because someone
wrote before you that they knew less
than you so just because someone wrote
in a medieval period and therefore
didn't have the benefits of modern
understanding that we have that we can
only read them to learn from their
mistakes and not to learn the truth
about political life or the human life
that we may have lost in the period
between then and now
so one principle of reading is the
utmost respect for what a great thinker
has written you don't try to interpret
him in terms of the surrounding culture
because you can't really make sense of
the surrounding culture without
understanding the works of
great thinkers that belong to it so to
try to understand a thinker in light of
his culture is sort of to put the cart
before the horse to a certain extent
well you see you can't understand asin's
if you don't understand Plato it's not
the other way around to answer to a
certain stand so something else about
Strauss ian's is that they see a
conflict again this is a generalization
but applicable you know for that reason
most of the time a conflict between
philosophy and law or philosophy in
politics because politics is the domain
of opinion and philosophy tries to
transform opinion into knowledge that
can have the effect of undermining the
beliefs that are necessary for political
community or undermining the foundations
of a legal order because you're
questioning what maybe should be taken
as an axiom so the conflict between
philosophy and politics or between
philosophy and law is a theme for
Strauss ian's as is the relationship or
the tension between philosophy on one
hand and Revelation on the other so the
life lived according to what man can
know by himself with his own efforts and
the life lived according to obedience to
a super human authority and it's not
trivial because the divine law or the
revealed law or the role of religious
belief has been of decisive importance
for Western tradition so the theme of
philosophy versus law of philosophy vs.
Revelation is crucial and incidentally
it's also related to how Strauss reads
texts because his view was that let's
say that I'm a member of a religious
community I'm a medieval Islamic thinker
and I'm also a philosopher so I now live
in a community constituted by the Sharia
by the revealed law of the revealed code
of Islamic law or in the Jewish context
by the Torah by the you know the
revealed code of Jewish law and at the
same time I see that it rests on certain
assumptions like for example that the
world is created as opposed to eternal
for example okay or that there's a
resurrection of the body or the soul so
there are certain beliefs that are
inherent to these religious communities
but as a philosopher
I in this example can't rest can't leave
it at the belief I actually have to
think about it right is the maybe the
work maybe the arguments for the
Eternity of the world are stronger than
the arguments that the world was created
after all they have in their favor
Aristotle whose kid who's no random
person right he's a pretty serious
thinker he didn't think the world was
created we got to take him seriously but
as a thinker in that context I can't
just come out and undermine the beliefs
that hold the community together so
Stroh said in such circumstances a
philosopher sometimes will employ
strategies of writing that basically
communicate two messages one message to
the superficial reader and another
message to the far smaller set of slow
thoughtful careful readers and he made
more he put more on the table than
anybody else had done before the methods
of writing that a philosopher in that
situation will use so for example
deliberate contradictions another method
that he mentions is that sometimes you
have an author who repeats himself and
he says like as I said earlier but the
repetition includes a modification as
well of what was said earlier so if
you're reading carefully you see that he
said one thing first and then something
else later and you're supposed to notice
that if you're the right type of reader
and you're not supposed to notice that
if you're the wrong type of reader in
other words it protects the opinions
that are necessary for the community and
it also subjects them to questioning for
the puppies of the philosophical race as
he put it somewhere for the for the
young men who love to think that is
fascinating that with that context
reading Bronze Age mindset by Bronze Age
pervert I don't know if you've read that
that really puts that book into context
because he I know he's probably say
Strauss e'en and I know that he
certainly has studied the ancient texts
quite a bit but the writing style there
was definitely more than one audience in
in the in the in the way he was writing
it and some of it was intended to push
people away and some of and the rest of
it was the sort of hidden messages for
the people who were really think
about it and paying attention to it can
you recommend any books by Biden Strauss
here that actually speaks to this sort
of technique because I'd like to check
that out personally the source book is
called persecution in the art of writing
and that's where he says in general why
this type of writing was needed why it's
a problem and why it hasn't been noticed
until he basically put a light on it and
then he also has a few studies there of
medieval thinkers where he tries to show
you how they did this and how to read
them if you read them with this in mind
but persecution in the art of writing is
the main text for that all right I'm
gonna have to add it to my never-ending
pile of books yeah you know it's
actually I heard you mention on another
conversation that people are studying
and you're studying Aristotle or maybe
people that in the circles that you are
with you know they might look at Plato
or something like that
and Strauss is view which is very
important for us if we're trying to gain
an understanding of these thinkers is
that it's not just the medieval who were
in a context of a religious community
but it's also more generally any
philosopher always is threatened by the
city and a threat to the city and
therefore it's also always going to be
characteristic of philosophy - of self
understanding philosophy to write in
this careful way so one of his great
discoveries I think is that he provided
new access even to Plato and Aristotle
by saying hey you have rushed so far in
your interpretation here with modern
suppositions and with modern assumptions
that you missed these beautiful details
these nuances these tucked away little
gardens in the in the texts that you
won't see if you don't read them knowing
that Plato may have used these methods
himself and why he may have after all
the love of Plato's life
Socrates my man in that sense okay are
the love of Plato's life was killed by
the city for corrupting the youth and
for not believing in the gods of the
city that cannot but have left
fact on plato's understanding of the
civic responsibility of philosophical
writing you see so in other words Stros
is a great guide to the ancient texts
because he understands how they wrote
got it I love it I'm gonna have to check
it out one of the things that aside from
the content the style an Aristotle that
I've been reading recently so dismissive
and just kind of Curt and funny and it's
it strikes me I can see it in this seem
to lab Saul's writing also too it's just
and enough with that argument like it
just it's so dismissive it it's just
like it's it's subtle and you can just
see somebody being disgusted and waving
their hand and be like ah and enough
with that and on to the next one but I
appreciate that I'm gonna take a look at
that alright so now I want to move into
lets I'm gonna sort of give you a chance
to take this in the direction of how you
think we should couch this conversation
let's just assume that I don't know
anything about Alexander Dugan I've
heard you know he's a Putin's Rasputin
he's the man behind the man and he's
driving this new political vision and
and the geopolitical vision for Russia
in the 21st century that's all I know
okay I want to know what that means what
is he thinking
is it real what influence does he have
who was he influenced by is he related
to a Nazi Heidegger Heidegger is a Nazi
right like for real but not in a bad
sense I don't know I don't know any of
these things these are the things I want
to learn these are the conversations
that I want to have and you know I want
to sort of just open it up now that we
have this context we know that you're
here for the pursuit of knowledge and
for understanding for the sake of and
you know we're both sort of renegades
out there so let's have let's have this
conversation and walk me through it this
is Dugan for dummies on Jack Murphy live
with Michael Miller line let's Milliman
let's let's do it buddy so I would say
that for the circles that you're in that
I'm in that you know Claremont American
mind whoever's thinking about somehow
maybe has heard something about you know
even if they don't know the names
they've heard of loosely I think the
starting point is this idea a place
where I started of the fourth political
theory
it's the name of the first book of his
that was published in English and it's
something that he himself saw and sees
as the cutting edge of his thought as a
political theorist and so I think it's a
good place to start
all right the basic idea of the fourth
political theory is as follows the 20th
century was a struggle of ideologies
liberalism communism and fascism because
those the first second and third
political theories and it includes also
their variants okay shades of liberalism
shades of communism is shades of fascism
by the end of the 20th century
liberalism was the last ideology
standing some people declared that
moment liberal triumphalism they said
this right yeah the end of history the
basic idea that we have come to the last
if history is the history of
philosophical ideas and here you
philosophy
we have the last great philosophical
idea human rights universal freedom the
state that guarantees individual rights
and freedoms all of that liberalism was
seen as it had its triumphalist moment
however he says what if you reject
communism which you do he does fascism
which she says is to be rejected but
also liberalism well here you're not
really left at first with any obvious
alternative because those three
exhausted the ideological space in the
20th century and by the time liberalism
came out victorious
there wasn't a coherent ideological
alternative now people start to talk
populism this that but strictly speaking
there was no obvious theoretical
alternative so he says this is the
initial gesture or montmartre logical
moment of the of the fourth political
theory if we reject all three of
liberalism communism and fascism and we
don't want to get caught up in the trap
of believing their exhaustive that they
exhaust all the alternatives we should
declare the space of a fourth political
theory and just that first declaration
the naming the carving out of a
contextual space for thinking already
gives you a breath of fresh air from
what is on the other side of it right
from having to choose between those
three and I just want to give
I'd hear okay because one of the reasons
this resonated with me personally when I
was at university British Columbia back
in the day
I was reading Strauss and I had an
interest in Israel okay the State of
Israel and I noticed that all of these
things were immediately called fascists
this logic still happens every day today
not just with Strauss not just with this
room with a million other phenomena
they're called fascists and if you look
at it you see the logic if you're not a
liberal and you're not to the left of
liberal there's nothing else you could
be conceptually about fascist in that
model and therefore you sort of
understand why everybody lumps you
together with that title but the problem
is that those three do not exhaust the
options right they don't exhaust the
possibilities so he declares the space
of a fourth political theory that's
already an accomplishment he says in his
book that I don't understand why people
who don't hear about the fourth who hear
about the fourth clinical theory don't
open a bottle of champagne and celebrate
that now they can think freely outside
of liberalism communism fascism but then
you get to the next step and you say
okay well alright you've cleared a space
that is says what it's not can you say
anything about what it is or what it's
positive components might be and here
his analysis is something as yeah so
let's stop it yeah so you said positive
components defined as what it's not
clarify so the negative is were not
going to be the first second or third
political theory that creates the space
for thinking but then you can say well
what is going to be in that space and he
does have something to say about that
like as an option
that's what but if you're saying it's
it's it's does it reject all the tenets
of liberalism or is it just saying this
is not like a holistic adoption of
liberal so I'm like can is this saying
like individual rights bad here's how he
puts it oh I'm gonna give you my image
for it so imagine that each of these
liberalism communism fascism is like a
house of cards okay so it has components
but it's a whole thing so he says you
can perform the following operation you
can break the house of cards
in other words break the whole ISM as
you said of this system as an ideology
and now you're left with just its
component pieces that have been to
switch metaphors there
biological charge has now been like
removed from them you see they've been D
ideologized and just become components
you see so he says what we could do is
we can perform this operation we can
dismantle the conceptual schema or house
of cards of each of these systems and
then look to see what of the pieces that
are left over can be used used in
thinking about our alternatives so
here's how he says that should be done
he says in each case how do you make the
house of cards fall he says you have to
reject some key component of each theory
and when you reject that component it
will no longer be an ideological hole
and when it's no longer an ideological
hole you can pick from it so in
liberalism he totally rejects the idea
of the individual he says you don't have
liberalism without the idea of the
individual so I'm going to reject the
idea of individual and from liberalism I
can borrow its emphasis on or what's
useful in the construction of a fourth
political theory is the emphasis on
freedom but what's anathema is the
definition of the human being as an
individual and also the notion of
progress
so he says same thing in communism what
we're going to reject is linear
temporality the idea that history
progresses to from point A to point zero
point Z is going to be as it is in that
model we're gonna reject the linearity
of time we're also going to reject the
class centric analysis because it's not
he doesn't say class isn't important but
he says class is not all-important so
you reject the centrality of class but
he says we're going to adopt as useful
and as significant its critique of
capitalism so there after all there are
profound insights in in communist
political theory about the drawbacks of
capitalism and from the third political
theory fascism which by the way I should
add he in the book he says fascism on
one hand and Nazis among the other he
distinguishes them they're both variants
of the third political theory in Nazism
he rejects the emphasis on race and on
supremacy and in fascist political
theory he rejects that statism because
they're separate things and fascist
political theory after all is just
- distorts light looks like a
deification of the state so he says
we're gonna reject all of that but what
can we borrow so if we borrow freedom
from liberalism as you know important
category we borrow the critique of
capitalism from communism what could
possibly be of value in the third
political theory especially if you've
rejected you know race and supremacy and
statism so he says that you can borrow
the notion of the ethnos now the ethnos
is not the race and Dugan has a textbook
on ethanol sociology which i translated
it's available in english and you get
there an understanding of what he means
including his rejection of racism what
he means what schools of thought he's
drawing on and why the ethnos might be
important and he says liberalism and
communism they totally erased the idea
of the ethnos of let's say of the of
what studied in cultural anthropology he
said they didn't really have space for
that and could you can you define it for
me well basically it's the study of it's
a study of societies from their simplest
to their most complex but it doesn't
interpret the sus the society as a
result of abstract individuals coming
together it interprets society as a
result of a shared community of language
and belief that shares a view of its own
origin now he says though it's not a
question of whether that belief is or
isn't accurate because we're not dealing
with the genetics we're not dealing with
race we're not dealing even with natural
science we're dealing with cultural
anthropology with social science with
the logic of belief and with the
structures of society so in his that
mythology book let me just say briefly
he goes from the simplest which he calls
the ethnos to another model which he
calls in russian than that would you
could say it's sort of like the folk or
the people but not a people like an
agglomeration of individuals the people
where you say like German people or
Spanish people okay so you have the
ethnos you have the multi-ethnic folk
then you have the nation like the
nation-state civil society global
society and post society so it's a whole
model of social structures and
complexity and for example social
stratification
the figure of the Shaymin the figure of
the philosopher Oh the figure of the you
know bourgeoisie so it's actually a
whole analysis but he says there's no
room for that really in these other
models and there were thinkers who were
somehow within they weren't liberals
they weren't communists they're called
conservative revolutionary thinkers
there was sort of like internal
dissidents against the Nazi regime to a
certain extent or take julia Savola he
criticized italian fascism but from the
right so these are all figures that are
important for Dugan and he says look
that's just something that we can draw
on not to necessarily reproduce it one
for one but it's a theoretical useful
theoretical resource for the
reconstruction or new construction of a
political alternative that's one of the
things that the fourth political theory
is and he says actually this lit this
liberate sus from his point of view to
study it like if you no I am NOT third
political theory second political theory
or first local theory you can then study
the resources of those thinkers without
feeling like you're identifying with the
total ideology so there may be something
valuable in Derrida and doulas or in
somebody else where you take those
aspects of thought without buying the
whole ideology so somehow his method is
to free up the serious reconsideration
of all of these ideological alternatives
not to reproduce them but to borrow and
somehow be inspired by if need be I have
many questions the first question that
comes to mind is what does it mean to
reject the individual but embrace
freedom whose freedom if not the
individuals so the great question very
natural question to ask so his view is
that I think the simplest way to see
what he means is that there's more to
being a human being than being an
individual individual is an
interpretation of a more basic
experience called being human and the
concept of individual is already it's
somehow a constraining over
interpretation of this broader
experience of being human that doesn't
exhaust what it means to be human it
actually limits it it could be
it's a useful limitation in some ways it
produces certain results not all of
which are a problem but it somehow
blocks genuine access to what it means
to be human and I should add that Straus
a sorry Dugan says that's true of
identification of us as class
consciousness as well as identification
of us as race or as status he says all
of those interpretations of human
existence are misleading they're all
they missed the mark and they obscure
the phenomenon so one of the key
components and this is where we open the
door to Heidegger and things get even
more philosophical than they have been
up to this point of the analysis he says
okay if we're gonna reject the
individual we're gonna reject the class
we're gonna reject the race and we're
going to reject the state what will be
at the center of the fourth political
theory and he says it's going to be the
it's going to be what Heidegger calls
and in his works das eine in other words
the most basic human existence that
hasn't yet been obscured by self
interpretation you see and he says if we
take das eine as the fourth political as
the actor or agent or center of the
fourth political theory we now have
access to the whole philosophical
apparatus methodology terminology and
everything that Heidegger puts on the
table without falling into any one of
the three political theories because
although it's true that Heidegger was a
member of the Nazi Party it's not true
that his philosophy is properly
characterized as a Nazi philosophy and
for those people who may be listening
who don't buy it I appeal to the
authority of Strauss who said that it's
not enough to understand how to curse
thought the fact that he was a Nazi but
we don't need to appeal to cirrhosis
authority you can look at Heidegger zone
writing or take my word for it
so Dugan says if you put das eine or as
I say this our human being that hasn't
been constrained yet in its self
interpretation at the center of the
political theory there's a notion of
freedom there that is not reducible to
or identical with the liberal
understanding of freedom you see and
it's not there's no expectation that we
know what that means
right away right I mean after all he had
to write books on Heidegger and develop
this idea and but one of the beautiful
things for example he has a book where
one of the titles is experiments and
existential politics because this hasn't
really been done before in this way but
he's saying if we want an alternative to
the status quo we're going to have to
rethink some things from a new
perspective we don't just want to
recycle liberalism versus leftism
leftism versus Nazism Nazism versus
liberalism he's like stop that and let's
go deeper or let's go up or let's go
around let's find a new ground a new
foundation a new topology or topography
and Heidegger is at the center of that
for him and this most basic human
existence that hasn't been limited by
self interpretation is it even possible
to acknowledge or understand that that
state of being given that in order to
even acknowledge it you have to implore
some level of self interpretation or
analysis yes so it is but it's a return
because we always find ourselves already
in a mode of self interpretation right
we we're never encountering ourselves or
the world or anybody else uninterpreted
so we're already in a set of
interpretations that's fine Heidegger
acknowledges that he has to because it's
the fact but the question is can you
return from the understanding of that
fact or from the observation of that
fact too can you sort of turn your
attention to your set to the act of
interpretation and to the fact that
you're self interpreting being and that
gets the ball rolling so Heidegger
acknowledges the circularity here you
can never get outside of interpretation
but you can sort of as he puts the point
is not to get outside of the circle but
to get into it in the right way to see
how it's operating and to move from how
we normally are namely assuming that we
already know what's what not taking our
interpretations for granted or
interpreting but without a clear
understanding of how we're doing that or
what or in what terms and returning to
ourselves in our basic constitution and
ground that's Heidegger largely I mean
the his 1927 book being in time
that isn't an attempt to affect that
return of our thinking and our atonement
to the being that we are I returned from
our normal everyday experience of
ourselves and others and so it's very
much of a reorientation but it's
definitely not a black box it's not an
unattainable you're not trying to get to
a perspective that is outside of
everywhere quite to the contrary he says
you can't do that and scientific modern
scientific philosophy and other
movements that that claim they can get
to a perspective that's not anywhere are
an example of missing self
misinterpretation you see it mm-hmm
so it avoids both like cultural
relativism on one hand and strict
scientific objectivism on the other and
it avoids them by going deeper to a
deeper foundation so Heidegger is a
revelation in that sense okay I'm
putting my brain to this as best I can
there's a storm so many questions so in
summary do getting rejected out of
liberalism communism fascism / Nazism
one that the individual to linear
temporalities and the class centric
analysis that means like capitalism
necessarily leads to communism etc and
that in communism
there's the focus on the the property
owners and the workers and that's sort
of the fundamental basis for for the way
the entire society is founded that's
very Marxist thought right and then also
rejected the emphasis on race and
statism from fascism and nazism accepted
from liberalism is a sense of freedom is
also from communism accepted a critique
of capitalism so that begs a begs a
question is not the right thing it
brings up the question what would be in
its place and then third accepts from
fascism or Nazism this idea of ethnos
which is not race but I wrote down a
shared imagine order is that some as I
found write that does OK shared imagined
order to me that sounds like Hariri and
the book sapiens that I've read a few
years ago about us organizing around
imagined stories right that's the way
that we gather it struck me is
when people say civic nationalism is
that similar in do you think is a civic
nationalism like but people would
purport that we have the United States
not based on race some people say not
based on race but based around an idea
and concepts is that would that fall
within this ethnos idea yeah and dunno
well in Duggan's model it's a form of
society civic nationalism and the
society that sees itself as as based
around an idea or comprised of
individuals related in such in such a
way but what he says is that in all of
these social organizations from the
simplest to the most complex so for
example you can say even beyond the
American idea you have the idea of
global citizenship right where you're no
longer art it's not civic nationalism
it's like global identity right
globalism and beyond globalism you have
the identity that rejects even human
identity and begins to say a post human
post social order where no what matters
is what we have in common with all
sentient beings or maybe at some point
with just all life period right so in
that total model he sees civic
nationalism as one among a number of
alternatives but the crucial thing is
that in no case is the smaller shared
ethnic identity erased it's only pushed
deeper and deeper down in the basic
fraction you know so it's like that it's
always there ethnic identity is the
simplest identity even in a complex
society so it's again he has a model on
it it's hard to necessarily to walk
through it in detail but he definitely
has an account of civic identity and of
the shared national idea as opposed to
like a more narrow tribal order or the
globalist alternative that's all in his
in his work got it okay so I'm starting
to see the picture here and so we've
rejected some things we've accepted some
things and now we're starting to put
some things into the box and one of them
was this the idea and I I didn't get the
exact name but it came from Heidegger
about the most basic human existence
that has been limited in the past by
self interpretations right boss this is
das I am alright I sign okay
so now we've added that what else are we
adding to the mix okay so at one point
Dugan says the following that the fourth
political theory has you could see it as
having like a body soul and spirit which
correspond to the following disciplines
the body is geopolitics the soul is
ethno sociology which we discussed
briefly the spirit is theology and the
deepest Center is Heidegger so this is
just another way of seeing it it's a
total it's not just the philosophical
model it's also a worldview that tries
to reconfigure the disciplines like the
scientific disciplines so let me tell
you what I mean he says in our
prevailing model the the number one
disciplines are economics and law
liberalism is fundamentally economics
and law so the rejection of liberalism
would be something else it wouldn't just
be another form of economics and law it
has a totally different Constitution of
the sciences and geopolitics becomes an
important component of that for him now
there's another big discussion here but
he put his money where his mouth is in
the Russian context and made geopolitics
a thing in Russia you could say he's
established a Russian school of
geopolitics he had admit he had a great
influence as I understand in military
circles after the collapse of the Soviet
Union because they found themselves
first of all really without a clearer
without a clear enemy without a clear
identity without a clear self
understanding and he drew on the
resources of classical geopolitical
thinkers who see the division between
land power and sea power and some other
components like this and he began
teaching courses on geopolitics and
later the is geopolitical a textbook
became assigned reading and geopolitics
became a discipline in Russia where you
could see that NATO the logic of like
American Western NATO activity and the
meaning of the Russian opposition to
that so that's some some of that was
known about Dugan when I started my work
that he's a geopolitical thinker because
some of his main your reputation and
works
had to do with that for example the
infamous book foundations of geopolitics
but almost nobody really knew these
other aspects of his thought even though
they were available but just nobody
seemed to have paid much attention to
them so you have the geopolitical level
of analysis you have the ethno
sociological level that's sort of where
you're talking about like he's got this
view that in liberalism there's
civilization and the uncivilized there
like the civilize the savage and the
barbaric
so there's civilization is one standard
like you're civilized or you know you're
not you're developed or you're
underdeveloped it's sort of just one
thing civilization it's a state that you
attain but his view drawing on some of
his predecessors was that there's many
civilizations that civilization is
plural you can't reduce every groups
experience if an Indian Islamic African
so on and so on or this whole register
of civilizations
you can't just map it on to the self
understanding of the West so partially
that level of analysis that's the
ethanol sociological level so
geopolitics civilizational studies or
ethnic sociology and then theology this
is all this is the thought about the
gods about the divine about the sacred
about revelation or eschatology the end
of times the beginning of times and he
says again this is part of his
disciplinary worldview like he says
theology should be a hundred times more
important than economics and and law you
see it as should these other disciplines
but Heidegger is the is the center of
all of this because after all dougen i
say my characterization not too
misleading i believe he's a
philosophical supremacist okay
not only do ghen I think Strauss and
Heidegger are also philosophical
supremacists and it's interesting to
wonder how you could be a philosophical
supremacist and still have these very
divergent positions but for Dugan the
philosophy is the highest human activity
in the philosophers in a way the highest
human type so he couldn't leave it at
geopolitics atma sociology and theology
so therefore Heidegger is the radical
center of all of that and somehow he
tries to correlate geopolitics
to a heidegger's thinking you know
cultural civilizational studies to the
resources of Haida garyun philosophy and
likewise with the theology and he's got
a lot of books on on these I've taught
some of them I've read some of them not
all of them true and translated this is
a massive project of political
philosophy designed to present a well
grounded well articulated genuine
alternative to the ideologies of the
20th century not some marginal not some
marginal leftist circus anti global ISM
something rooted founded justified in
touch with the greatest thinkers that we
know and with the most deepest
disciplinary contributions that people
have made and it's this massive project
needless to say he doesn't do it all by
himself he leads seminars he has other
people who contribute to this project he
himself calls it sort of an open
undertaking he's written that he doesn't
want it to become a closed Dogma because
it's got to live with the openness of
das with three da signs freedom as soon
as it becomes a closed ideology that's
all dead he knows that it can become a
parody of itself in a simulacrum he says
that but it's a risk that you take when
you think ghent genuinely you know that
that somebody else takes it and makes it
into a cheap parody of a cell for some
you know not scible meme or something
but his view of it I think is a serious
top-to-bottom rigorous tremendous
monumental project of political
philosophy that passes through the
almost universally acknowledged giant of
20th century thought Heidegger so it's
the real deal
from my perspective in my view which
doesn't mean we have to buy every part
of it or agree with every step in the
reasoning but it's definitely not
reducible to Dugan is this or Dugan is
that you talked to Alex Jones therefore
I won't read his book he's got a big
beard and looks like rest boot and
therefore he's trying to infiltrate our
institutions it's something else
and those are some of its components the
historical context for this is it
possible that this is a wounded
intellect so the end of the 20th century
it is the end of history people say
right liberalism try I'll try
over everything communism failed fascism
Nazism was defeated and you're living in
Russia who's not a liberal society I
think you're either faced with accepting
liberalism as your dominating you know
ideas of culture and society or left
trying to come up with something else
so is this this is like a reaction to
communism x' loss in the competitive
world of ideologies in the 20th century
yes and no so no because there were
alternatives there were other parties at
the time that were not liberal like in
movements and things like that radical
nationalists and others but actually
it's a total it is wounded intellect in
the sense that he looked at the Soviet
society he looked at the Soviet ideology
he looked at around even in the 90s to
see some of the alternatives and all of
it became sort of a bankrupt for him but
here's the question what happens
existentially to us when we have a
wounded intellect
that's wounded so deeply that basically
it stands naked before itself for the
first time when it looks around and all
the scales have fallen from its eyes or
when it's become deeply disillusioned so
the fact that if we say it if we
interpret his experience as a wounded
intellect we say that's actually the
moment when in a sense it's the moment
when you can see most clearly and when
you can see most profoundly when you
have that when suddenly everything that
you're familiar with and everything that
you've taken for granted has lost its
meaning for you Heidegger analyzes that
he says when we're usually in the world
with things with beings drinking coffee
doing this doing that but at some point
we enter this exit we we can have this
existential moment where everything has
become meaningless for us and that
throws us back on ourselves and actually
gives us access to ourselves for the
first time in a genuine way so I would
say in a sense and he he doesn't say
wounded intellect but he has an account
in some of his books of a moment just
like this where he discovered the sort
of like the meaninglessness or emptiness
of the moment but some people discover
it and they do go to the bottle or
something like that but he discovered it
and it was
sort of like an initiate like sort of
like a mystical magical initiation into
a whole world of undiscovered
alternatives so it is a crucial moment
for him but just it's not like you know
my country lost and I need to come up
with an alternative I somehow you know
want to regain stature in the world I
mean he says in some of his books
he's very critical at times of Russian
conservatives not liberals and of
Russian nationalists when he says you
guys are putting forward alternatives
with no self understanding no
philosophical grounding you have no clue
what you're talking about you don't know
what it means to be Russian because
you've never thought about what it means
to be and so he's not just running to
any alternative
he actually had this ground come out
from under his feet he landed somewhere
and from that somewhere is now somehow
rebuilding and read and everything takes
on a different hue from that perspective
you know what I mean so the whole
phenomenon and again this is not going
to be may be fully comprehensible at
first pass but what the intellect itself
is when you say wounded intellect right
the whole question of what the intellect
is what is our intellect what does it
mean to think that for him is a question
of the first priority in fact he's doing
a series of lecture courses now on
YouTube where he just the most recent
one he just finished this is on
heidegger's reading of Aristotle and on
the tradition of phenomenology from
Brentano Husserl and Heidegger he just
did a lecture on the intellect the
active intellect in Aristotle and it's
phenomenological meaning and I'm going
to tell you only someone who has had the
type of alumina Tory experience that he
has had could conveyed this topic in
such a profound and moving way so the
might in a way my defense of Dugan over
the years it's just among other things
because it's there's yes there's the
know your enemy type reasoning yes
there's the I always thought how can we
have anybody in our government working
on Russia who doesn't actually study
Russian thinkers that's like just
doesn't make any sense to me you want to
study their audio logs that's obvious
there's nothing more to talk about I
guess that's not it not everybody sees
it that way
but even separately from all of that
even separately from like oh he's an
interesting political theorist on the
philosophical level there is something
that he had that he's conveying that is
just very worthwhile inherently valuable
I can relate a hundred percent to having
a moment of existential crisis I can
relate a hundred percent to having
everything that you thought was
important sort of torn down in front of
you and giving you that opportunity to
reflect and look deeply in words and and
taking advantage of an opportunity to
rebuild something that seems to make
more sense than the thing that you lost
it one of the questions I'm struck with
right now is and maybe I'm totally wrong
about this about liberalism liberalism
to me is like a process not an end goal
whereas I kind of felt like communism
and fascism Nazism is is an end goal
rather than a process liberalism seemed
to be a system to find truth
whereas communism told you what the
truth was is and maybe I'm wrong in that
but is the fourth this fourth political
theory is this a is this a system for
finding truth or is it the truth and is
that a meaningful difference is that a
distinction worth identifying or you
know I don't even know I'm out of my
element here this is the Dugan for
dummies I'm asking questions let's let's
see where they go yes so there are a set
of base you could say there's a basic
set of shared beliefs or of dogmas that
a simple adherent of the fourth
political theory would have so in that
sense it's like you know you think
there's not not just one civilization
but many civilizations that you reject
the superiority of natural scientific
thinking to other ways of thinking okay
you accept the relevance of divinity and
human life okay and and so on so these
are somehow shared elements they have
their philosophical counterpart or their
theoretical counterpart where you get
into the details and there are open
questions and it can be more
experimental but I'm saying for the
average you know
person who just imagined someone is just
in living in Duggan's if there's a state
that adopts this as an ideology not
everybody is going to go around talking
about Heidegger just like not everybody
goes around talking about Hobbs and
Machiavelli and Locke right it's a
relatively small group that digs into
the theoretical foundations so it has
its dogmas in that sense but it's meant
to be fundamentally concerned with truth
it's not a like there are political
theories today in the US and elsewhere
that our premise on the rejection that
truth exists at all right they say there
is no truth there's nothing to attain to
there's basically what we agreed to and
you talked about this I think in your
last episode on post-modernism to a
certain extent right I had the pleasure
a good discussion there so this idea
that you can reject just truth doesn't
exist it's whatever we agreed to it's
whatever we as power relations or
something that's that is not ours not
Duggan's view instantly also not
renounce Roces view not Heidegger's view
but it's a trickier question in each
case what truth means for them so one of
the things Heidegger is is known for or
one of the things that he made central
to his questioning is what is truth what
is the essence of truth what what what
what is what is truth and so he said we
commonly take it as the correspondence
of what we say with something in the
world so if if I say my coffee is warm
and my coffee is warm so my sentence
corresponds to the object and therefore
the sentence is true so truth is like a
property of sentences that do or don't
match external reality that's one way of
looking at what truth is okay he thought
did not think that that was fundamental
he thought that that was derivative he
doesn't say that is not no you know if I
do it's not truth about my coffee is hot
or cold no that's not he says but he
says that's not the fundamental
experience of truth or what it means so
he's got a lecture course called on the
essence of truth ray says look you talk
about a true friend or you talk about
you know true let's say true gold or
something like
not okay authentic truth and true in the
sense of real or authentic but what do
we mean by real so the whole question of
what is an object what is reality how do
we correlate language to what exists and
what is even the act of judgment all of
that again it's a philosophical level
but there's no getting around it because
when we begin to ask what is what does
it mean for something to be true we're
not gonna answer that in any really in
any other way right besides looking at
the opinions that people have eventually
we got a scratch down beneath the
surface so he's Heidegger had a more
basic I mean a more fundamental
understanding of truth that dougen takes
over and I won't go into all of the
details of it but it's neither the
postmodern rejection of there being
anything that you can say it's not a
total anti reality in that sense but
it's also not limited to the correct
description of objective reality this it
is something different but it's not anti
truth it's not post truth it just says
there's a more basic notion of truth
that we have fallen away from it's kind
of like this I'll give you an image that
may or may not be helpful imagine that
you have a closed door on one side of
the door is a bright light and we're on
the other side okay we open the door and
the light shines through and then the
door begins to close and close and close
and close and close until it's shite
Heidegger saw the history of Western
philosophy approximately like that
there's one moment where the light comes
through very clearly and then the rest
of the time it's somehow being removed
from us up to the point where we come to
nihilism and to the view that there is
no truth there's just power that means
the door has closed again the light is
on the other side of the door okay so
there's not just truth there's the
history of truth there's the
transformation of truth through the
arrows or through the epochs there's
what truth was when the door first
opened with the pre Platonic s-- there's
truth as it was when the door began to
close and Plato and there's truth when
the door is shut and the camera man has
taken the lights and put the back at
storage in modern nihilism you know
modern technological nihilism so the
question is can we open the door again
and we don't it's almost like we don't
even know what's on the other side of it
is the lights though there is something
else there we don't know because it's
not been we don't even know there's a
door there anymore it's been so long
since we
to open it so the in some sense all of
these thinkers their job is to remind us
hey guys there's something over there
let's go have a look let's knock let's
feel it out if it's locked let's find
the key as some of them click say they
opened it we don't know for sure right
we've got for now we have to walk for
now we don't even know there's a door
so truth is something with the history
truth is something that has a
development but what does that even mean
so this is all an undiscovered uncharted
territory I think you know it's uh but
it's in my view it's where eventually
thoughtful figures will need to turn
because the question of human being of
being of truth of history all of this is
at this somehow whether we know it or
not at the center of the ground that's
shaking beneath our feet somehow it's
almost like there's a knock from the
other side of the door you know and it's
saying hey you forgot about me and I'm
not saying it's god that's over
interpreting all that we know is there's
something calling us to see that the
light has gone out and to me that's the
whole drama in the whole mystery of
where things stand right now
dougen falls in there Heidegger Strauss
they all sense it and there you go
that's why that's the sort of the truth
the issue or problem of truth it's it's
sort of a mystery not just something we
either reject or assert it's hard to
follow up buddy yes all of that as I'm
taking notes I'm struck with the
question you said that the fourth
political theory has as an underlying
assumption or a belief that there are
many civilizations does that make it
like a civilizational pluralist it
believes that there are multiple
civilizations of equal Worth and value
or is that one civilization or type of
civilization that is preferred or better
what does that do against view is that
there's a four ality of civilizations so
that's number one there's a plurality of
civilizations and in each civilization
there
is going to be a few different basic
types of thought roughly like a
materialistic type of thought that
rejects everything except for what you
can see touch feel smell eat taste
there's going to be something like a
[Music]
vertical topography where you want to go
up so and each sin each civilization
there's going to be some form of like
the mystic or prophet or philosophers
someone who tries to ascend beyond to
waste to a more real world to the ideas
or to the you know demean to break
through somehow to a deeper reality and
in each culture of civilisation there's
going to be something like a middle
ground and all of their variations so
he's done actually an analysis of it's
got a 24 volume book of philosophical
analysis of civilizational plurality
based on these philosophical methods so
as I say no I don't recommend you know
I'm not saying anybody should go and
work through all 24 volumes they're not
even in English yet but yeah so many
civilizations and in no case can you
assume that you've really understood
them from your own point of view so
basically he's saying look let's take a
basic example if a Russian person wants
to know the West he can't just assume
the West is worse than Russia or the
West is better than Russia where the
West is equivalent to Madonna and
McDonald's or whatever you know back in
the 90s maybe that reference is more
appropriate it's like you actually have
to go and study the poets and the
philosophers and the and the writers and
you have in sort of in that case you'll
get to know the American cultural soul
so to speak and same thing if you want
to go study some Spain or Brazil and all
of these are multifaceted I said in my
interview back in the day one of the
phrases that got me in trouble but it's
as true today as it was then he's
pointing to a blossoming complexity of
human existence so cultural and
civilizational multipolarity it reflects
the blossoming complexity of human
existence it's its languages its songs
its dances and also as I say the deeper
dimension how it how it thinks about
time how it thinks about God how things
about history I'll think so
and he says we shouldn't reduce we
shouldn't take any one of them as the
standard for all the others of them it
doesn't mean that somebody who is just
like let me give you this example from
Strauss so Strauss said culture used to
mean
cultivation like the cultivation of
nature I have a garden I have some
flowers I'm cultivating them so that
they grow but people have started to
talk about culture like there's a
culture of prisoners there's a culture
of gangs there's a culture of rapists so
a culture got away from the sense of the
cultivation of human nature and started
to mean just any set of ordered activity
and cirrhosis view was like now it's
kind of like we've littered our garden
with cigarette butts and you know Peter
pissed on it we don't even care so we've
moved away from the actual notion of
genuine cultivation so Duggan's view is
not that you know the cigarette butts
and the public urination is as equally
worthy as the philosophical life or of
poetry it's just that there are many
Gardens and there are many flowers that
are growing in those gardens and that's
where he wants to turn his attention and
is he thinks that should be reflected
politically to a certain extent in a
multipolar world and philosophically by
you know the correct study of the
alternatives so this is a great point
something to really talk about one is it
does liberal of the liberalism account
for a civilizational plurality one and
then two
does it account for a multipolar world
that reflects these civilizational
polarities and three to what extent is
this notion of multipolarity
civilizational ii really feeding the
geopolitical view and i think is what's
really getting in people's you know the
MER and people saddle when they start
hearing about multipolar world because
from the United States perspective
that's not exactly what we have or what
we want or what we see for the future
right yeah so generally speaking liberal
political doctrine or liberal political
philosophy or just liberal thinking
doesn't really acknowledge plurality
cultural civilizational plurality in a
meaning
full you know in an adequate way so it's
not just that it denies the Worth and
value the unique Worth and value you
know of other cultures and civilizations
it recognizes them the same way it
recognizes the individual dignity of
individuals but it doesn't recognize
them in their own self understanding
self interpretation and self estimation
I would say that's it's a rejection of
plurality in space but it also in a way
rejects I mean this is a sort of
Strauss's point to a certain extent that
the liberal mind also doesn't grant it's
also very high-minded
and how would you put a demeaning of
previous times so it also looks at past
times as not really worth they're just
you know they're pre-modern they just
are not yet what we are now and
therefore are not really worth our full
attention
that's the temporal aspect or they're
underdeveloped you know they just
haven't gotten as far today you know
here and now as we are here now so the
it takes itself as the standard in space
and in time so in that sense liberal
world is not really pluralistic in the
deep sense of acknowledging the Worth
and uniqueness of the other cultures and
civilizations
it also accordingly you know doesn't
really respect a multipolar world so
Dugan had an analyze this and he says
the west can do like multilateral
approaches where other governments
together with the United States will
pursue a certain policy so it can work
together with other states other blocks
and other forces but without really
caring about or you know cherishing
their distinct cultural identity and
also obviously any power wants to
preserve its power and seize the rise of
other powers as a threat and as a
problem whether you dress it up as
blossom in complexity or not it doesn't
matter right you don't want to give up
your hegemony you don't want to give up
your power you don't want to cede the
momentum all of that is totally
understandable obviously and is
justified to a certain extent and also
well defended by other political
theorists in our tradition but still you
asked right there's the liberal world
sort of have an embrace of multipolarity
the answer's no although to a certain
extent with Trump
that that changed to a certain extent he
gave speeches now this is not my main
area of expertise but he gave speeches
in defense of national
self-determination and cultural
self-determination in Poland and
elsewhere and there were figures like
Ernesto Russo if I said that correctly
in Brazil who took that and wrote about
it and made a big deal out of it
so that marked a break you know what the
past approaches but definitely it's not
inherent to liberalism in the way that
it is to let's say eurasianism to give a
name to do against ideology and it's
Russian outfit to acknowledge these
differences so multipolarity is kind of
like an official doctrine for Russia
there shouldn't be just one poll in the
world but again that's obvious enough
right we don't want the United States to
be the sole dominating force in the
world and on the other hand for the from
the United States not to want there to
be other competitors so all of that is
very natural but still it you have to
raise the question on what basis is
there going to be the assertion of
multipolarity
is it just the power struggle does it
reflect something else right is the
theory just addressing of the power
games or do the power problems arise
because they grow out of the theoretical
problems you know so there's a bit of
both of that I would say but if Dugan
didn't have volume after volume after
volume of genuinely theoretical
philosophical work it would be very easy
to say these are all just power games
but more often than not the the thinking
comes first and then the power relations
arise from within what has been
configured in thought you see so if you
go to Heidegger and if you combine them
with these other things and you have
cultural uniqueness and distinction then
you have this whole question of
multipolarity so Duggan's been fighting
for it politically by trying to make a
block various blocks and geopolitical
allies for russia he's been trying to do
it domestically and in international
politics but again I argue that that
reflects his deeper world world view
it's like again the geopolitics in his
model on his own account for what it's
worth we don't have to accept it but on
his own account we should at least take
it as a starting
point geopolitics is the body right of
is the body of the discipline ethno
sociology to solve theology to spirit
and Heidegger the center of all of these
things so in a way it's not that the
body is not important but the body is
just one component and it's not like the
body is more important than the soul you
know if anything the soul is more
important in the body so there's a
geopolitics there's a defensive
multipolarity but it's supposed to
reflect what he thinks is the truth
about civilizational plurality Russia is
a really big place right and Soviet
Union spanned a number of different
areas Europe Asia I remember in college
I used to date girls the Russian girls
in some way someone look another way
than I dated a Kazakh girl you know
there's like a whole tremendous variety
of people that were within the the
Soviet bloc and and living within Russia
Russia's massive place right it's both
Europe both Asia to what extent is is
that that experience bubbling up through
these ideas right because it has to sort
of if it doesn't take into account the
natural phenomenon of multi-ethnic in a
way and and multipolar world then it's
sort of just discounting its own
existence and its own yeah I think
that's a good point so there's the
experience of of the many groups there's
also the experience of having lived in
the Soviet Union so you have the idea
not just of non politically organized
groups but also politically organized
groups and of a union or an empire that
embraces them all as well as the history
of the collapse of the Soviet Union into
the Russian Federation as a smaller and
distinct form of government so all of
that is therefore dougen and is thinking
about political life and political
reality no doubt and it's easier for him
to put his finger on these types of
things than it is in a just a stable
long lasting Civic nationalist country
where you haven't had components of
crisis you haven't had the same moments
of crisis and the same thing is coming
to the surface as you said so for sure
all of that factors into his
into his thinking and into his
theorizing hmm
fascinating one of the second things
that I wrote down here was reject
natural thinking what did I write that
down right or is that could you explain
that this was this was right after
acknowledging many civilizations and
right before accepting the divinity of
human life in between there was
rejecting natural thinking did I did I
get that money if said rejecting the
natural science so the idea that natural
that scientific study of objective
reality is the standard for human
knowledge and the height of human
perfection that basically our task is
not scientific knowledge of reality and
the use of what we discover in
scientific study of reality the
technological implementation of those
discoveries for the improvement of our
power efficiency comfort levels and all
of that
that is basically usually considered to
be you know modern outlook there the
scientific conquest of nature as the
standard for the relief of man's estate
we live better when we put the products
of scientific discovery into practice
but that print that privileges in a
sense scientific consciousness over the
over other experiences and other again
not not less intellectual but not
necessarily scientific rationality as a
description of objective reality so I
can only say that there was a group of
thinkers huh Cyril Heidegger and others
phenomenological thinkers who said we
can look at pre scientific not primitive
culture society you know X amount of
years ago but in us ourselves what is
the pre scientific mode of our own
thinking and consciousness in what sense
is scientific thought a modification of
our pre scientific mode of consciousness
again not in time we're not talking
about some cave men here we're saying
how is our consciousness itself
constituted in relation to scientific
knowledge and scientific modes of
thinking that school basically was
phenomenology I looked at pre-scientific
it studied consciousness in ourselves
and it's precise
civic forum through certain methods that
it used to get to that and without again
going into all of the details the basic
view here is not to take the scientific
mind as the peak standard so why why for
example is the scientist on the peak of
the mountain as the perfection of the
human intellect and not the poet you see
or the scientist and not some other form
of human intellectual activity so
because I call Dugan a philosophical
supremacist he does take intellect in
some sense as supreme but he doesn't
reduce the operation of the intellect to
modern scientific rationalism neither by
the way ever enough to emphasize just
for the record neither by the way to
Strauss so Strauss himself also learned
from Husserl and Heidegger also rejected
this the primacy of scientific knowledge
without becoming some anti scientific
postmodern leftist needless to say right
am I remembering my Aristotle right when
he says that the political like
political thinking political thought is
at the top of the mountain that that is
the highest pursuit the best pursuit
yeah I should bring you the most utility
and happiness and knowledge yeah it's
it's one of the peaks of one of the
mountains but it's definitely a peak of
a mountain there's a question there of
there's an age-old question of the
primacy of the political life to the
philosophical life and whether or not
you need the peak of the political life
to experience the peak of the
philosophical life but no doubt
reflection on politics on ethics on law
on community on the law giver on the
virtues excellence justice and
everything that is at the heart of
political life no doubt is one of the
two peaks if there are two in Aristotle
got it and so the third element here is
accepting the divinity of love human
life
reserve is that bringing in necessarily
concept of spirituality and religion
into this fourth political pork
political theory no and I would say if
you get it yeah so there is okay he puts
it like this he says if we reject
liberalism communism fascism we make
available the things that they rejected
one of the things that they rejected is
rkx traditionalism revelation divinity
they had maybe each of them had their
own watered-down version or somehow
narrow version but the whole resort all
of the resources of mythological
thinking again traditional thinking
religious thinking and it need not be
religious rationalism deism
Protestantism suddenly it puts on the
table again doesn't force-feed this but
it puts it on the table all forms of
mysticism Gnosticism hermeticism magic
okay all the mechanisms and modalities
of religious thought that may have been
in the underground in modernity if not
completely rejected so first of all
those become available for our study and
reconsideration and Dugan has a book in
search of the dark logos where he looks
at Gnosticism hermeticism cabbalistic
thinking alchemy and these other things
that for liberal rationalism would
definitely be just definitely crackpot
domain right you do not take that's not
seriously even if you're even aware of
its existence so that's number one he
puts it on the table but it's not but
it's also not jumping to theology and
divinity right away because again there
- what is the soul right all they're all
open questions in a sense the simple it
for a Russian Duga nest the simplest
thing is to just say I mean identify
with my traditional religious identity
Russian orthodoxy and there you go so
Russia is distinct from the West because
the West is Protestantism and
Catholicism and we're Eastern Orthodoxy
end of story
I'm Russian Orthodox there you go that's
my cultural distinction but and dougen
allows for that at one level but again
as you always see there are these
multiple levels so at one point he says
and this is available in English in the
book called political Platonism he says
that there should be a reconsideration
of the origins of Christianity and of
the various schools and debates in
Christianity but all of that will be
proceeding blindly if it doesn't know
Plato and Neoplatonism because all of
those really
thinkers somehow you get the blueprint
or the matrix of their thought in at
least Plato and Neoplatonism broadly
speaking so when he says III had
mentioned about one of the basic views
of a fourth little theory is that
divinity is not rejected right it's just
it's not it's on the table it's not a
materialism it's not an atheism it
somehow allows for that trans human
domain domain but it ranges all the way
as they say from I'm just gonna declare
my Russian orthodoxy to be in conformity
with my cultural tradition - I now need
to do the whole study of neoplatonism
and Plato to understand what was going
on with the early church fathers that's
all fair game what's not fair game is
materialism just to say there's nothing
but the rocks and the trees and the
birds okay no other dimension but what
you can see in swallow basically that is
off the table I think he I should add
though to the extent that there that
Russia is a unique civilization this
just follows from his model Russia would
also have its unique materialism so even
the forms of like transcendence and
materialism okay they also will take on
different hues somewhat from
civilization to civilization so it's a
rich picture but yeah it doesn't mean
everybody has to believe in God it means
somehow like I said an acknowledgment of
this other domain dimension or aspect of
human life is sort of built in again
there is a lot there it's a little off
topic but I'm reminded of and just been
reading recently the conflict between
the founding fathers in America not the
conflict even but the the the symbiotic
relationship between the the sort of
cosmopolitan enlightenment thinkers and
the rural they were even Zionists
thinkers at the time in like
revolutionary America people who thought
that Americans were were actually Israel
right like they were in the wilderness
and they were - God's people and they
were there to create new society and and
very fervent religious spirit in the
countryside of the United States
I've been reading sermons from I
1750 in 1760 and it's it's very intense
but there was a dance and an interplay
between the cosmopolitan folks at the
city who wanted to embrace these
enlightenment and in thinking and
thought and liberalism and create this
new country and have the revolution but
you know it was an alliance it was a
dance and it's interesting to me that I
have to go back and rediscover those
were that relationship between the very
religious groups that were on the ground
at the time and you know the the
separation of church and state and this
whole concepts that we think of today
were that the United States government
isn't involved in or founded by or you
know supports of religious thinking when
really the whole revolution was had very
serious heavy religious undertones and
overtones and those things all sort of
gotten lost and what's interesting for
me and my personal upbringing is my
mom's side the family was Catholic but
she sort of was reformed she lost it and
my dad's side was Jewish and I was bar
Mitzvahed but then I sort of lost it and
and so now I'm I'm I grew up without any
kind of religion and without any kind of
real spirituality and now I've been
taking time to actually go back and look
and learn and read and understand and
and I've been developing a much greater
appreciation for that's type of thinking
and these processes and starting to put
things into historical context you know
like a guys guys like Plato and
Aristotle what did the what do the
Christian Christian scholars think about
you know is is Aristotle in heaven you
know he wasn't saved by Jesus right but
like it seems you know the thinking is
very similar and right all along the
same line so it's just fascinating to me
to see these questions from two and
three thousand four thousand years ago
to you know American Revolution to forth
political theory all these questions
still still circulate none of them
necessarily answered am I right about
that we haven't answered any of these
questions yet well you know strokes has
this essay called progress or return and
it's the sort of the logic of return
returning to the questions
returning to the roots returning to the
age-old fundamental problems of human
life and human political life of law of
how history can be distorted or created
or rewritten what gets left though when
founding fathers have debates among
themselves about what's fundamental so
it sounds like you and I and Dugan and
Heidegger strokes each in their own way
you know as has gone to the logic of
return which doesn't just mean going
back to what's old and outdated because
these questions are always alive for us
they're always living they're always
giving and they're always worth our time
and attention so it's a it's great that
you're doing that and I think a lot of
people are beginning to because they see
that they're not satisfied with the
answers or even with the questions that
are available to them now and instead of
looking forward into an abyss or into
some confusion or chaos they're taking
their bearings with what with the
possibilities of return and I think
that's a worthwhile project well I mean
as far as I can tell the science demands
these types of questions you know the
more you learn about the universe and
time and space and the the more it
demands these kind of questions and then
the happier I am to embrace them and
honestly I've been hearing more and more
people say I grew up without religion I
actually grew up anti religion and today
I'm more open to the notion of religion
than ever before and I have that same
sentiment and that comes through what
I've found to be a rational process
which contradicts everything that I ever
had presupposed about spirituality or
religious thought that there was a
rational thought process involved in it
but as the more I go through the more
layers I peel back you know and the more
questions we get down to the fundamental
questions you know you do have to what
is it accepted avidity of human life at
some point right we have covered a
tremendous amount of ground here it's
about two hours is this is this a basics
have we gotten the basics covered is
there some element that we have left out
do we want to wrap on this is there
something to expand upon where how would
you feel do you think I've gotten a 101
inch
dougen at this point is there something
else we need to hit on I think it's good
for a 101 you have the fourth political
theory
yeah Heidegger the geopolitics ethno
sociology its importance for Russia the
notion of many different civilizations
his anthea liberalism which is a
relevant factor for sure is trying to
network and meet with other people who
reject liberalism sometimes for
geopolitical purposes sometimes for
Theoretical purposes that's all part of
the picture I think that's good as a 101
I only want to add that it's been
important for me and I think there's a
good reason to highlight it again people
who listen to you who are hearing this
conversation let's say they know they
know Strauss okay and somehow more let's
say how would you put it like if Dugan
still seems far out and far off and kind
of wild or crazy because you can still
take this conversation go look at them
online and still think no there's no way
we're talking about the same guy here
they look you know but I just want to
say that the problem of the political
meaning of philosophical supremacy the
problem of reconsidering the crisis of
modern rationality the problem of
digging into alternatives that are
neither fully collapsible to liberalism
communism or fascism is just so
important for us to do and Dugan is not
the only one Strauss and others are
doing the same people on the left people
on the right these are questions that
are alive for us and we should be
willing to look at whoever is making a
contribution to that question I think
you've done an admirable job getting
Dugan 101 across and I hope that your
listeners find him to have been a good
contribution to the discussion well I
sincerely appreciate your time and your
effort I can certainly relate to your
experiences with your PhD and canceled
culture and just the just running into
just a complete disrespect for
intellectual exploration basically and
the the elimination of a play space
intellectually and the elimination of
the opportunity to explore and express
without having everything that you do or
say or purse
you talk to be established as your
personal lifelong cannon that which
should be on your tombstone of which you
should be judged by at all moments in
time I can certainly appreciate that
experience that you had I've had it lots
of people are having it we're having our
own Dugan desk moment of you know the
walls come crumbling down and you're
left wondering what is important who is
important who's right who's wrong
I can imagine for you you know if you
grew up wanting to be a PhD having the
echod Academy and such high esteem you
set your goals on it you were probably
dreaming about it when you were younger
and then you get there and you become
disillusioned and now you've yourself
had a moment of sort of in the
wilderness and trying to figure out what
you think and where you want to go and
how you want to pursue your intellectual
journey and your process and so I think
I find a lot of community with people
like yourself and others who have been
willing to take those risks you know I
suspect that this is a risky
conversation for me to have if I were a
normal quote normal person but you know
I don't care I love this kind of stuff
on the edge and frankly you have really
put into context a lot of some of the
other conversations that I've had
earlier with Bronze Age pervert with
Ryan Williams from the Claremont
Institute it put unmei helping me
understand astrouski in perspective and
Dugan and and so I really appreciate it
thank you very much hopefully we can do
this again after all this has sunken in
maybe we can do a 102 class after this
maybe get into Heidegger a little bit
more as I my interest turn in that
direction as well but thank you very
much Michael I sincerely appreciate it
where can people find you how can they
interact with you what's your website
Twitter handle all that stuff Michael
Miller mandazi a is my website you can
see some of my writings and interviews
and videos there and I'm on Twitter it's
M underscore Miller Minh so I'm on
Twitter you can feel free to ask me
questions there if there's anything you
want to follow up with or just write to
me and I'd be happy to see you there
so that's that's really it I have videos
up on YouTube but it's all through
Michael Miller Minh dossier alright
fantastic thank you so much for your
time sir thank you everybody for
listening
Jack Murphy live.com liminal order
liminal - order calm democrats are the
plural that's the book check it out hit
subscribe see you guys next time Jack
Murphy live show Michael thank you so
much have a great day talk to you soon
[Music]
you